<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<eml:eml xmlns:eml="https://eml.ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.2.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:stmml="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.2" packageId="87cdb923-4e9e-40eb-9ab0-d1ac50e3f0af" system="uuid" xsi:schemaLocation="https://eml.ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.2.0 https://eml.ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.2.0/eml.xsd">
  <dataset>
    <title>A long-term (1986-2010) phytoplankton dataset from the LTER-Italy site Lake Candia</title>
    <creator>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Alessandro</givenName>
        <givenName>alessandro.oggioni@cnr.it</givenName>
        <surName>Oggioni</surName>
      </individualName>
      <electronicMailAddress>cre</electronicMailAddress>
    </creator>
    <pubDate>2023</pubDate>
    <abstract>This georeferenced dataset describes a 25-year (1986-2010) monitoring studies of phytoplankton abundance and biomass in Lake Candia, a eutrophic, natural, small, and shallow lake located in north-western Italy. The lake has been subjected to biomanipulation experiments aiming to improve its water quality since 1986 to 2010. It belongs to the national (LTER-Italy), European (LTER-Europe) and International (ILTER) long-term ecological research (LTER) networks. Making available this dataset also represents a contribution to the current activities of the LTER networks, aiming at making accessible the time series of the LTER sites, in order to reconstruct trends and dynamics and to identify and compare reliable trends and can be useful for further ecological and biodiversity studies on small and shallow lakes. The interest of the dataset is also remarkable because Lake Candia belongs to the national (LTER-Italy), European (LTER-Europe) and International (ILTER) long-term ecological research (LTER) networks, where the long-term site-based monitoring approach and the site comparison are important to determine spatial and temporal trends and changes.</abstract>
    <keywordSet>
      <keyword>occurrence</keyword>
      <keyword>Darwin Core</keyword>
      <keyword>GBIF</keyword>
      <keyword>occurrences</keyword>
      <keyword>phytoplankton</keyword>
      <keyword>LTER-Italy</keyword>
      <keyword>Lake Candia</keyword>
      <keywordThesaurus>...</keywordThesaurus>
    </keywordSet>
    <intellectualRights>Creative Commons Attribution (CC-BY) 4.0 License</intellectualRights>
    <coverage>
      <geographicCoverage>
        <geographicDescription>Lake Candia is located near the city of Tourin in the northern-western Italy and belongs to the Italian, European and International Long-Term Ecological Research (LTER) Networks: Candia (https://deims.org/c7fe4203-24b1-4d11-a573-99b99204fede).</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>7.8982</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>7.9222</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>45.3327</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>45.3185</southBoundingCoordinate>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <temporalCoverage>
        <rangeOfDates>
          <beginDate>
            <calendarDate>1986-03-06</calendarDate>
          </beginDate>
          <endDate>
            <calendarDate>1987-12-02</calendarDate>
          </endDate>
        </rangeOfDates>
      </temporalCoverage>
      <taxonomicCoverage>
        <taxonomicClassification>
          <taxonRankName>Species</taxonRankName>
          <taxonRankValue>Asterionella formosa</taxonRankValue>
          <taxonRankValue>Melosira varians</taxonRankValue>
          <taxonRankValue>Chrysococcus</taxonRankValue>
          <taxonRankValue>Dinobryon divergens</taxonRankValue>
          <taxonRankValue>Mallomonas akrokomos</taxonRankValue>
          <taxonRankValue>Mallomonas</taxonRankValue>
          <taxonRankValue>Oocystis</taxonRankValue>
          <taxonRankValue>Pediastrum duplex</taxonRankValue>
          <taxonRankValue>Sorastrum</taxonRankValue>
          <taxonRankValue>Sphaerocystis schroeteri</taxonRankValue>
          <taxonRankValue>Staurastrum gracile</taxonRankValue>
          <taxonRankValue>Woronichinia robusta</taxonRankValue>
          <taxonRankValue>Drepanochloris nannoselene</taxonRankValue>
          <taxonRankValue>Closterium</taxonRankValue>
          <taxonRankValue>Cosmarium</taxonRankValue>
          <taxonRankValue>Franceia ovalis</taxonRankValue>
          <taxonRankValue>Planktolyngbya limnetica</taxonRankValue>
          <taxonRankValue>Synedra radians var. radians</taxonRankValue>
          <taxonRankValue>Merismopedia</taxonRankValue>
          <taxonRankValue>Scenedesmus</taxonRankValue>
          <taxonRankValue>Ceratium hirundinella</taxonRankValue>
          <taxonRankValue>Closterium acutum var. variabile</taxonRankValue>
          <taxonRankValue>Lemmermannia triangularis</taxonRankValue>
          <taxonRankValue>Schroederia setigera</taxonRankValue>
          <taxonRankValue>Rhabdogloea smithii</taxonRankValue>
          <taxonRankValue>Peridinium</taxonRankValue>
          <taxonRankValue>Phacus tortus</taxonRankValue>
          <taxonRankValue>Ankistrodesmus falcatus</taxonRankValue>
          <taxonRankValue>Tetraedron minimum</taxonRankValue>
          <taxonRankValue>Limnothrix pseudospirulina</taxonRankValue>
          <taxonRankValue>Microcystis aeruginosa</taxonRankValue>
          <taxonRankValue>Oscillatoria planctonica</taxonRankValue>
          <taxonRankValue>Closterium gracile</taxonRankValue>
          <taxonRankValue>Elakatothrix</taxonRankValue>
          <taxonRankValue>Staurastrum avicula var. lunatum</taxonRankValue>
          <taxonRankValue>Tetraedron trigonum</taxonRankValue>
          <taxonRankValue>Mallomonas tonsurata</taxonRankValue>
          <taxonRankValue>Dictyosphaerium</taxonRankValue>
          <taxonRankValue>Uroglena</taxonRankValue>
          <taxonRankValue>Fragilaria crotonensis</taxonRankValue>
          <taxonRankValue>Cryptomonas</taxonRankValue>
          <taxonRankValue>Rhodomonas</taxonRankValue>
          <taxonRankValue>Dinobryon</taxonRankValue>
          <taxonRankValue>Chrysidalis</taxonRankValue>
          <taxonRankValue>Mallomonas caudata</taxonRankValue>
          <taxonRankValue>Coelastrum</taxonRankValue>
        </taxonomicClassification>
      </taxonomicCoverage>
    </coverage>
    <contact>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Alessandro</givenName>
        <givenName>alessandro.oggioni@cnr.it</givenName>
        <surName>Oggioni</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>CNR - IREA</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>Via Alfonso Corti 12</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Milan</city>
        <administrativeArea>MI</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>20154</postalCode>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
      <phone>000-000-0000</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>cre</electronicMailAddress>
    </contact>
    <methods>
      <methodStep>
        <description>
          <section>
            <title>General Protocols</title>
            <para>
      Field methods. All experiments will be carried out in the
      greenhouse at Harvard Forest. We have developed an instrumentation
      system that allows us to collect continuous dissolved [O2]
      measurements: dedicated micro-probes (DO-166MT; Lazar Research
      Laboratories: http://www.shelfscientific.com/) connected to
      multiplexers and data loggers (AM16/32B multiplexer, CR-1000
      datalogger and control system [Campbell Scientific:
      http://www.cambellsci.com]). The initial ecosystem composition in
      all experimental plants will be standardized by seeding each
      pitcher with a 10-ml inoculum of liquid collected from pitchers
      growing at Tom Swamp. In all experiments, prey will be supplied to
      pitchers as standardized aliquots of dried and finely ground
      bald-faced hornets (Dolichovespula maculata; Hymenoptera:
      Vespidae), which we collect in quantity throughout New England.
      Both hornets and ants (the latter are the dominant prey of S.
      purpurea) are hymenoptera, and have nearly identical C:N ratios
      (hornets: 3.97; common bog-dwelling ants [Tapinoma sessile and
      Myrmica lobifrons]: 3.37), but on average hornets have greater
      than 100 times the dry mass of these ants, and are easier to
      collect and process as a standardized food source. Additions of
      prey, either as large <quote>pulses</quote> or chronic
      <quote>presses</quote> are analogous to the enrichment and
      eutrophication that occur in aquatic <quote>green</quote> food
      webs in which phytoplankton abundance is boosted through addition
      of limiting nutrients. In <quote>brown</quote> food webs such as
      the Sarracenia microecosystem, detritus - not primary production -
      is at the base of the web, and our treatments boost this material
      as would happen through increases in arthropod prey capture78 or
      through nitrogen-enriched precipitation.
    </para>
            <para>
      Proteomic analysis. Proteomic profiles of microbial communities
      are determined after separating the microbial fraction from the
      pitcher fluid, prey, and other detritus. The microbial
      <quote>pellet</quote> is subjected to SDS-PAGE (sodium dodecyl
      sulfate polyacrylamide gel) electrophoresis; bands are cut out and
      digested in-gel with trypsin. Tryptic peptides are subjected to
      LC-MS/MS (liquid chromatography tandem mass spectrometry) for
      peptide and protein identification. Absolute abundance of peptides
      and proteins are quantified using AQUA (Absolute QUAntification)
      analysis109.
    </para>
          </section>
          <section>
            <title>Specific Experiments</title>
            <para>
      Experiment #1. Effects of nutrient enrichment on state changes and
      [O2] profiles. This experiment alters nutrient enrichment rates to
      characterize the [O2] profile and the transition to the anaerobic
      state. The experimental design is a one-way layout with 5
      treatment groups: one control (no enrichment) and 4 enrichment
      levels (0.125, 0.25, 0.5, 1.0 mg prey added ml-1 d-1). One plant
      is assigned to each treatment group, and the entire set is
      replicated 6 times over successive weeks. [O2] is monitored
      continuously for 4 days to characterize state changes and tipping
      points under different enrichment rates. This experiment tracks a
      continuous [O2] profile but does not include proteomic analysis.
      The purpose of Experiment #1 is to identify an enrichment rate E
      that generates a long pre-tipping period before transition time T
      to the anaerobic state. This enrichment rate will be used in
      Experiments #2 - #4.
    </para>
            <para>
      Experiment #2. Identification of early intervention time and
      characterization of aerobic and anaerobic proteomes. This
      experiment will use the single enrichment rate E determined from
      Experiment #1 and impose different intervention times I at which
      nutrient enrichment will be terminated. Thus, this experiment will
      identify the latest time I* at which it is possible to intervene
      and stop the transition to the anaerobic state by halting
      enrichment. The [O2] profile will again be monitored continuously
      over 10 days to measure the state of the system. From Experiment
      #1, the transition time T to the anaerobic state with no
      intervention will be known. We will use one control group (no prey
      addition) and ten levels of intervention time (all with the same
      enrichment rate E) as a proportion of T (0.1, 0.2, 0.3, 0.4, 0.5,
      0.6, 0.7, 0.8, 0.9, 1.0). Six plants will be assigned randomly to
      each of the 11 treatments in a randomized one-way layout and [O2]
      profiles will be monitored continuously. In addition to the [O2]
      profiles, we will also characterize the protein profiles of
      aerobic and anaerobic pitchers in all 11 treatment groups at the
      end of the experiment.
    </para>
            <para>
      After the plants are harvested, we will create proteomic profiles
      of the predominantly bacterial portion (centrifuged pellet) of the
      pitcher fluid from each plant, as described in General Protocols.
      Thus, 66 separate pellet-fraction samples will be analyzed by
      SDS-PAGE. After examining the SDS-PAGE profiles, approximately ten
      proteins that show dynamic patterns consistent with state change
      and five that do not change will be cut from the gel, subjected to
      in-gel tryptic digestion and a portion of the tryptic peptides
      will be analyzed by LC-MS/MS. Using these data, we will choose
      three identified peptides from each protein for peptide synthesis
      such that each synthesized peptide contains stable isotope labels
      (AQUA peptides) to distinguish them by mass from the native
      peptides. We will then quantify all 45 of the native peptides from
      the original samples using a known amount of each AQUA peptide
      spiked into the tryptic digest. The AQUA analysis of proteins that
      do not show changes will be used for normalization between
      samples. These data will be used to independently identify the
      current state of the system and forecast the time-to-transition.
    </para>
            <para>
      We will use Sequest searches for initial identification of
      peptides; relevant scores including Xcorr and Delta Cn values will
      be given for each peptide. Other peptides will be identified by de
      novo sequencing using PepNovo; all PepNovo scores will likewise be
      given including any N- or C-terminal gaps. Mass error in ppm will
      be reported for each precursor ion. We will use standard
      multivariate analysis to search for distinctive proteomic
      profiles114 that characterize aerobic and anaerobic ecosystems, as
      well as ecosystems that developed with and without inputs of
      photosynthetic O2 and plant metabolites.
    </para>
            <para>
      Experiment #3. Identification of diagnostic proteins. Using
      Experiments #1 and 2, we will have identified an enrichment rate E
      with a long pre-tipping period and an intervention time I* before
      which mitigation and termination of enrichment will prevent
      eutrophication. Experiment #3 will characterize the mean and
      variance of the protein profile before and after I*. We are
      especially interested in identifying proteins that increase
      rapidly in abundance (or variance) well before the onset of
      flickering in [O2] and before the transition time T from the
      aerobic to the anaerobic state.
    </para>
            <para>
      A cohort of 100 plants all will be fed at rate E (determined from
      Experiment #1), with intervention time I* determined from
      Experiment #2, although no intervention will be used in this
      <quote>press</quote> experiment so that we can contrast proteins
      before and after the state change. At seven times before I* and
      three times after I<emphasis>, we will harvest 10 randomly chosen
      plants. At each prescribed harvest time, we will measure [O2] and
      collect samples from each plant for proteomic screening using both
      SDS-PAGE and AQUA analysis. This experiment will identify proteins
      that rise quickly in abundance during the pre- I</emphasis> period
      and can be used as early indicators of a future tipping point.
      Because different plants will be harvested at each time period,
      this is a one-way ANOVA design, with pre-and post- I* a priori
      contrasts. A randomization test will be used to determine whether
      variances in protein expression differ through time. During these
      analyses we will use the data from the AQUA peptides and from
      known amounts of protein standards, such as bovine serum albumin,
      to approximate the amount of protein in a given coomassie-stained
      SDS-PAGE gel band. The reason for doing this is to provide a fast
      <quote>real-time</quote> assay based just on expression in the
      SDS-PAGE. This rapid assay will be used in Experiment #4.
    </para>
            <para>
      Experiment # 4. Proof-of-application. This experiment will provide
      a benchmark test of our methods and their ability to correctly
      identify tipping points. A cohort of 100 plants will each be
      fitted with [O2] probes and started on the enrichment regime. Two
      times per day, we will collect 3 plants each, pool their contents,
      and conduct a rapid screen in the lab with SDS-PAGE for the
      diagnostic proteins that were identified in Experiment #3. We will
      use the protein expression in the gel to delineate an
      <quote>early</quote> and a <quote>late</quote> mitigation
      strategy. As soon as diagnostic proteins measured in the SDS-gels
      are at abundances that signal we are at 0.5×I* - approximately
      one-half of the way to the latest intervention time - we will
      randomly select one third of the remaining plants for mitigation
      and termination of enrichment (the <quote>early</quote> mitigation
      strategy). We will continue to harvest plants from the remainder
      of the cohort and monitor proteins. As soon as diagnostic proteins
      signal we are at 0.75 times I*, we will randomly select one half
      of the remaining plants for mitigation and termination of
      enrichment (the <quote>late</quote> mitigation strategy). The
      remaining plants (approximately one sixth to one third of the
      original cohort) will continue to be enriched. We will monitor
      [O2] in all 3 groups (no-mitigation control, early mitigation,
      late mitigation) until all plants reach a new [O2] equilibrium. If
      the protein markers are successful, the proportion of food webs
      that remain aerobic will be significantly higher in the two
      mitigation treatments than in the no-mitigation control.
    </para>
          </section>
        </description>
      </methodStep>
    </methods>
    <dataTable>
      <entityName>level1.RData</entityName>
      <entityDescription>R file (RData) that contain 2 datasets about density (cell/ml) and biomass (mm3/m3) of phytoplankton sampling in the montly campains from January 1986 and Dicember 1987 and counting by inverted microscope. The datasets are harmonized by structural, spatial, temporal, taxonomic, and semantic folowing the gudeline of eLTER RI</entityDescription>
      <physical>
        <objectName>level1.RData</objectName>
        <size unit="bytes">83450</size>
        <authentication method="MD5">b1043c1c46ef01446d92ba57a34fff6d</authentication>
        <dataFormat>
          <textFormat>
            <recordDelimiter>&#13;
</recordDelimiter>
            <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
            <simpleDelimited>
              <fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
            </simpleDelimited>
          </textFormat>
        </dataFormat>
      </physical>
    </dataTable>
  </dataset>
</eml:eml>
